<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The beginning and endynge of all popery, or popishe kyngedome</title>
            <author>Lynne, Walter.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06658</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17115</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108949</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844601</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844601</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9430</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06658)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9430)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 55:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The beginning and endynge of all popery, or popishe kyngedome</title>
                  <author>Lynne, Walter.</author>
                  <author>Joachim, of Fiore, ca. 1132-1202. Vaticinia.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Aldergate strete, by Iohn Herforde, at the costes and charges of Gwalter Lynne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1548?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Based on a German translation of: Joachim of Fiore. Vaticinia.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: set forth out of hye Almayne into englyshe by Gwalter Lynne.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and place of publication from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9430:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9430:1"/>
            <head>¶The beginning and endynge of all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, or popiſhe kyngedome.</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>scene with pope</figDesc>
                  <head>And then ſhall that wicked be vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, whom the lord ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume with the ſprete of his mouth, and ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy with the apperaunce of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge, euen him whoſe comming is after the workinge of Sathan.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9430:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9430:2"/>
            <head>The epiſtle. ¶To the mooſt excellente and worthye prince, Edwarde the .vi. by the grace of god, Kyng of Englande, Fraunce, and Irlande, defender of the fayth, &amp; in earthe ſupreme head of this church, of England and Ireland, immediatly nexte vnder god, and to his moſt deare vncle, Edward duke of Somerſet, lorde protector of all the kinges maieſties realmes and dominions, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernoure of his mooſt royall perſon: His faithfull and obediente ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte Gwalter Lynne, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the continuall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence of goddes grace.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN SATHAN</hi> percey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued the ground worke and founda<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of the papacie to be ſo weake &amp; ſlender, that it ſhulde not be able to ſuſtaine and beare, the weight of the great heap that he intended to erect and buylde theron: then dyd he (mooſte deare ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine) beynge the angell of darcknes, put on him the fourme of an aungel of lyght. And vnder that cloke, he endeuoured all that he mighte, to fortifye and ſtrengthen it: by the moſt ſacred and holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, to thintente that the impietie and wickedneſſe therof, might the better be cloked and hid. And ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore dyd he ſubtylly inuent, and diligently inſtruct all his faithfull children the byſhops of Rome craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely to wreſte and falſely to interpretate, this place of ſcripture in Math. Thou art Peter, and vppon
<pb facs="tcp:9430:3"/>
this ſtone or rocke I will buyld my churche. Vpon this foundacion, buylded he ſo ſtrongelye, and ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſo beautyfull and gloriouſe a peece: that all the whole worlde wondered therat. The wiſe and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men employed all their ſtudye to enlarge, and decke this princely palayce, and ſee of Rome. Yea princes and rulers, thought it their duty, to become labourers, &amp; drudges in the erecting &amp; vpholding of this ſo gorgiouſe a buldynge. Finally the mater was ſo handled, that thoroughe all chriſtendome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſee was taken for the fountaine and well of all mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie. Remiſſion and forgeueneſſe of ſinne, were not to be had in any other place then there. But now, that it hath pleaſed the lorde (accordynge to the wordes of his prophet Ioel) in theſe oure dayes (the latter daies of the worlde) to powre out of his ſpirite vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all fleſh, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this ſecrete and hid miſtery of abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble iniquitie, is come to lyghte, and ſo opened that the ſuckelynges and younge babes of this tyme, knowe more then dyd the auncient and gray heared fathers in the time of blyndneſſe and ignoraunce.</p>
            <p>That moſt victoriouſe &amp; triumpha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t prince, your dearely beloued and naturall father, perceyuynge that more then hell darkeneſſe, wherin we (his pore ſubiectes) were led: opened vnto vs the moſte holy and ſacred bible, wherin are declared the miſteries of this ſo gorgiouſe a buyldyng. Ceaſe not therfore (moſt graciouſe prince) to ſet forwarde this godlye worke that your father began. And to thentent that your graces louinge ſubiectes may know by what craft and pollicie this buylding firſt began, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde proceded, I haue thought good to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
<pb facs="tcp:9430:3"/>
out of the Germaine tongue into Englyſſhe, this little boke. wherin is declared what maner of thinges the biſhops of Rome were at the firſt, what was their eſtate and condicion, and what was their office or deutye. Then how they abuſynge their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice aſpired, and came to ſo inordinate honour and dignitie. Howe they leuinge Chriſt and his mooſte holy worde, enployed all their ſtudy to pleaſe men. The ſecular power was it that they loked for. And no dout it was that, and not Chriſt, that gaue to the byſhops of rome, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preeminence to be called fathers of fathers, and to be preferred before other biſhops. But becauſe ſo ſecrete a miſterie, can not wel be ope<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned without plaine demonſtracions: the Author of this boke hath moſt plainly ſet forth by figures, the eſtate, that this Antichriſt is in, hath bene in, or ſhal be in, euen to the day of his vtter diſtruction. Theſe figures are not of the authors owne inuencion, ne of late daies inuented: but they were found in aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient libraries aboue .ccc. yeres ſence. The common experience, that is daylye ſene of the greate blynde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ignoraunce of that time, wold moue your highneſſe to doubte of the truth, and veritie of this reporte: but to certifie your maieſtie therin, there is at this daye remaining in the abbaye of ſaint Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in Luyke, a table of great antiquitie, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge portrature of like matter. Wherby it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfeſt that the fathers of auncient tyme, ſawe in the papacie, the thinge that they durſt not vtter, eyther by wordes or writinge, but truſtynge that the time wolde come when men might be bolde to ſpeake it: they dyd in the meane tyme kepe it in painting and
<pb facs="tcp:9430:4"/>
portrature, that ſuche as could coniecture, might gather knowledge therby, &amp; that the thynge myght remayne tyll ſuch tyme as god had appoynted it to be declared bothe in wrytynge and wordes. The Author therfore of this little boke: hath not onelye added vnto theſe figures an expoſicion to declare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanynge of euery of them: but manifeſt ſcriptures alſo, to proue the thinges that they repreſente, to be true, ſo that theſe figures may appeare rather to be the figures of ſome Apocalipſis or reuelacion, then the inuencion of any man. The ſpirite of the lyuing god, the geuer of all goodneſſe, inſtructe you in al godly knowledge, that for the time of your reigne in this worlde, your highneſſe may vſe the ſword to you committed, to the honor of god, and wealth of his members, lyuyng here vnder your domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. And then no doubte ye ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioye the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that ſhall continue for euer. AMEN.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithfull and obedient ſubiecte Gwalter Lynne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:9430:4"/>
            <head>IN MONSTRVM QVOD libellus, iſte graphicè depingit, ad Lectorem Candidum.</head>
            <l>CApripedes Satyri: tetrae Stymphalides Hydra</l>
            <l>Dira: Canis Stygius: Gorgones anguicomae</l>
            <l>Igne Chimaera furens rapido: Scyllae<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> triformes:</l>
            <l>Monſtra<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſi qua uſquam fabula priſca refert:</l>
            <l>Portento huic noſtro uictricia ſagmina cedunt,</l>
            <l>Nec monſtro immani cedere turpe putant.</l>
            <l>Inceſta ſiquidem &amp; uecordae libidine feruet.</l>
            <l>Depaſcit<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> inopes, expoliat<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> bonis.</l>
            <l>Mille, quibus miſeros circumuenit, obtinet artes:</l>
            <l>Tutatur leges mordicus uſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſuas</l>
            <l>Vertice uittato ſtultè nimium<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſuperbit!</l>
            <l>In<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> pios flammis ſaeuit &amp; igne nocens.</l>
            <l>Orbis opes conquirit, opum ſinuoſa uorago</l>
            <l>Aeſtuat, &amp; nummis cuncta profana facit.</l>
            <l>Portenti nomen Peſtis tibi Maxima binis</l>
            <l>Exprimit haud dubiè, Lector amice, notis.<note place="margin">P. <hi>M.</hi>
               </note>
            </l>
            <l>Romuleae quan<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Pater auguſtiſsimus urbis</l>
            <l>Cenceri falſo iure proternus amat.</l>
            <l>Scilicet eſt turpis Dominae meretricis alumnus,</l>
            <l>Quam ſacri arcanum uatis adumbrat opus.</l>
            <l>Cui, genius pronus ſtudia in contraria Chriſto.<note place="margin">Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus.</note>
            </l>
            <l>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Graio nomen non malê fonte dedit.</l>
            <l>Nam uerè (mihi crede) pios qui torret: egenos</l>
            <l>Deglubit: ſceleri Praemia magna locat.</l>
            <l>Qui pede ceruices Regum premit imperioſo:</l>
            <l>At<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> tumet faſtu turgidus Arſacio:</l>
            <l>Venales<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> malis ſacros proſcribit honores:</l>
            <l>Obruit &amp; uerbi ſemina ſancta dei:</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:9430:5"/>Connubij<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſuis ſocialia foedera neſcit,</l>
            <l>Pacem almam frangit, diſsidium<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſerit</l>
            <l>Collidit<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> armis totum feralibus orbem:</l>
            <l>Foenerat: annonas aere flagellat iners:</l>
            <l>Diuinos<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſuis titulis poſtponit honores:</l>
            <l>Et redimi ſacris coelica regna docet:</l>
            <l>Monſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haec cuncta Deo patrans pugnantia, chriſti</l>
            <l>Dici hoſtem meritô, quis dubitare queat?</l>
            <l>Sollicito hunc ſtudio lector peruolue libellum,</l>
            <l>Sat ſcio, uel lectus ter, mage gratus erit.</l>
            <l>Non fuco, at uero depicta colore placebit</l>
            <l>Portenti facies prodigioſa trucis.</l>
            <l>Diſpeream, niſi uera magis, quàm oracula Phoebi</l>
            <l>Delphica, uel ſortes Diua Sibylla tuae.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>I.A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="Scriptural_passage">
            <pb facs="tcp:9430:5"/>
            <head>Paule in his ſeconde epiſtle, and ſeconde chapiter to the Teſſolonians.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Rethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we beſeke you by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng of our LORD Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; in that we ſhal aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble vnto hym, that ye be not ſodenly mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued from youre mynde, and be not troubled, nother by ſprete, nother by wordes,<note place="margin">2. pet. 3. a</note> nor yet by letter which ſhuld ſeme to be ſent from vs, as though the daye of Chriſt were at hande. Let no man deceaue you by ony meanes.<note place="margin">Danie. 9. c 1. Tim. 4. a. Luce. xi. c</note> For the Lorde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth not excepte the departyng come fyrſt, and that that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynne be opened, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſonne of perdicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary, &amp; is exalted aboue all that is called god or gods ſeruyce, ſo that he ſytteth as God in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of god, and boaſteth himſelfe to be God.<note place="margin">1. Co. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and. 6. c. Dan. xi. c</note> Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre ye not, that wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I was yet with you, I told you theſe thynges? And now ye knowe what witholdeth it, euen that it myghte be vttered at his tyme.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> (For the myſterie of the iniquite worketh alre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye, tyll he whiche now onely letteth be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the way.) And then ſhal that wicked be vttered, whome the LORD ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume with the ſprete of his mouth,<note place="margin">Iob. 15. d. Eſay. 11. a. Danie. 8. d. Ioh. 8. d. Deu 13. Math. 24 v</note> &amp; ſhall deſtroye with the appearaunce of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge: euen hym, whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge is after the working of Sathan with all lyenge power, and ſignes and wonders, &amp; with all deceueableneſſe of vnryghteouſneſſe among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that peryſhe, becauſe they receaued not the loue of the treuth, that they might haue bene ſaued.<note place="margin">zacha. 5. a. Rom a. 1. d.</note> Therfore ſhall God ſende the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtronge deluſion, that they ſhulde beleue lyes, that they almyght be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned,<note place="margin">Oſee 7. a</note> which beleued not the trueth but had pleaſure in vnrighteouſneſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:9430:6"/>
But we are bound to geue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes alway vnto God for you, brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beloued of the Lorde, becauſe that God hath fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begynnyng choſen you to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, in the ſanctifyenge of the ſprete &amp; in beleuyng of the treuth, whervnto he hath called you by our Goſpel, to optayne the glorye of our LORDE Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Therfore brethren ſtonde faſt, &amp; kepe the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which ye haue learned, whether it were by oure preachynge, or by epiſtle. But oure Lorde Iheſus Chriſt hymſelfe &amp; God our father, which hath loued vs &amp; geuen vs euerlaſtynge conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacyon, and a good hope thorow grace, comforte your hartes, and ſtablyſhe you in all doctryne &amp; good doynge.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>scene with pope</figDesc>
               <head>And than ſhall that wicked be vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red whom the lord ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume with the ſpirite of his mouth, and ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him with apperaunce of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge euen him whoſe comming is after the workinge of Sathan.</head>
            </figure>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9430:7"/>
            <head>¶The beginnynge and endynge of all poperie (beinge taken oute of certaine olde prophecies more then .ccc. yeres agone, here faythfully ſet forth to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendement of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente worlde, out of hye Almayne by Gwalter Lynne.</head>
            <head type="sub">The interpretacion of the wordes of chriſte. Math .xvi. Thou art Peter. &amp;c. whiche the pope aſcribeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hym ſelfe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He pope (becauſe his eſtate myght ſeme the hollyer) toke the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures and chriſt him ſelfe to defend and maintaine it withall As Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius Silla by the romaines, hauing vnder the pretens of goodnes dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered them from the Marianes, afterwardes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed the riche and honeſt men of them, impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſpoiled and kylled them. Myght not ſuch ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parte be plaied with vs? yes and it is (the more pite) come to paſſe alredy. And ſtyll he hath kepte vs vnder, with the wordes which Chriſt ſpake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Peter, Thou art Peter. &amp;c. which wordes in no wiſe do ſerue for his purpoſe. But commonlye is it ſeene, that all thinge ſo begonne, come to an euill ende, as is to be ſeene by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole popery. They might better haue ben ſuffred, yf they hadde ruled more w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> goodnes in peace and tranquillite then with rigour
<pb facs="tcp:9430:7"/>
and mere tirannie, yf they hadde likewiſe rather for geuen, then ſtill perſecuted to death. But truelye, the wolfe (the whiles he is in priſon) deuoureth no ſhepe, althoughe there were neuer ſo manye with him in captiuitie, but being at libertie, let euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beware of him.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſte ſaid to Peter. Mathew .xvi. Thou art Petrus. &amp;c. Petrusin the greake tonge, is as muche to ſaye as in the latyne tonge <hi>ſaxum.</hi> In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> englyſhe tonge a rocke, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of chriſt he was named a rocke, bicauſe he hadde ben conſtant in the knowledging al the holy catholique faithe, and not wauering hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and thither, as the commune people did. And vpon the ſame rocke, that is vpon the ſame ſtedfaſt knowledge of faith, will I buyld my churche. And who ſoeuer ſtedfaſtly ſtandeth to the ſame, the very hell ſhall not preuaile againſt him, muche leſſe ſhal men.</p>
            <p>Lyke as ſaint Auguſtine in his ſermon vpon this place dothe attribute theſe wordes, vpon this rocke, to our Lord Ieſu Chriſt, and not to Peter ſaieng, this is the meaning of it. Thou arte Petrus, and vpon the ſame rocke whiche thou haſt confeſſed and knowledged, ſaienge, Thou art chriſt the ſonne of the liuing god, wil I buyld my church, vpon me I wyll buylde the, and not me vppon the. But ſuche as wolde men to be buylded vpon men, ſaid thus, I holde of Paule, I holde of Apollo, I
<pb facs="tcp:9430:8"/>
hold of Cephas, which is Peter. The other ſort whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che wold not be buylded vpon men, but onely vpon the rock Ieſu chriſte, ſaide. I holde of Chriſte. &amp;c. <hi>Auguſtinus. Eraſmus Roterodamus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Maruell therfore (not a littell) that certaine people there be that wreſt and wring this place and forcely apply and aſſcribe him, to the pope as if it onely apperteined vnto him. But the why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les his churche (whiche he nameth the catholyke church) is not buylded vpon chriſte, but vpon hym ſelfe, ſo muſte lykewiſe the foundacion euen be ſo ſtronge, mightye and durable. Yet doth he ſet forth him ſelfe, with the holy ſcripture which in no maner of wiſe doth ſerue for him. Neither is Cyprian with him, where as he ſpeakethe of ſainte Peter, vppon whome the churche was buylded. For S. Peter in his confeſſion and knowledge, and the pope agree, euen as fier and water. what compariſon is there be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twene Chriſt and Beliall? if the popes both in faith and lyuinge were to be compared with Peter, ſo were there ſome hope to be hadde.<note place="margin">Math. v Mat. ix. Luc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. xiiii.</note> But whiles he is but a corrupte and vnproffitable lalte, hauing loſt his ſauour, wherto doth he ſerue? ſcaſſe to the dong hill? And therfore is he dekeied. Yet the pope that the ſcriptures wolde not maintaine him, he hathe ſought another meane or waie. As is to be ſene and redde in the popes Cronicles.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶How longe that the byſhops haue bene in the churche, and when, with the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge lykewiſe of the pope.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9430:8"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He chriſtians hadde but biſhoppes vntill the time of Conſtantine. An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>no .ccc. xi. And theſe byſhops did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſtudy the holye ſcripture, and taught the holy goſpell to the people, and exerciſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, &amp; liued ſoberly. The biſhop of rome had no dominion ouer rome as he hathe nowe, he was a curate vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; that was al. And biſhops generallye (according to their vocation) taught y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdom of god, &amp; comforted and fedde the poore. The communes gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mony with other neceſſary thinges whiche they dealed among the poore people, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles dydde lyke wiſe. There was moche ſpite wroughte againſte them by diuers great and mightye men. They were there to ſuffre. Fewe of the magiſtrates were of their ſyde, yf by chaunce one were with them tenne were againſt them: as both themperoures and popes Cronicles teſtifie,<note place="margin">The perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peple &amp; how they came togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> yet dyd they ſuffer al thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for gods ſake. Item the commune people labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red truelye and holpe one another, and where as they might be ſewreſt, there did they gather togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. So hathe lykewiſe the holy Anthony done in egipt, and brought many to chriſt, and they encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Inſomuche that there dwelt certaine thowſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of chriſtians in the wilderneſſe of Egipt, and li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued by the goſpell, geuinge them ſelues to mortify the fleſh, &amp; daily labours, This witneſſeth ſ. Ierom.<note place="margin">Ierom. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>BVt whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foreſaid Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinus Magnus had ouercome &amp; ſubdued cruell Maxe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius whiche perſecuted al chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, he gaue lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s being ſcattered abrode, to build chirches &amp; openlye
<pb facs="tcp:9430:9"/>
to preache the goſpell, geuinge them alſo certaine greate giftes towards the ſame, but not the citie of rome, neither yet landes nor people, as the pope al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth in his lawes.<note place="margin">Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus gaue not rome to the pope.</note> Diſtinct .xcvi. Conſtantinus, but kept them to him ſelf, his heyres and executors, &amp; Conſtantius his ſonne had the poſſeſſion of rome euen as Conſtantinus his father had before him. After Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius, Iulianus lykewiſe, Iouinianus Valentinianus, Gratianus, and ſo forth.</p>
               <p>WE read no where that the byſhop then inuaded the Romains, neither that he kept anye maner of warres,<note place="margin">Suche em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour ſuch byſhops.</note> but lyued poorelye. And the byſhop with the chriſtians were many times inuaded by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperoure.</p>
               <p>BVt when Iuſtinianus (after the birth of chriſt. v<hi rend="sup">c</hi> .xix.) became emperour, he redemed the byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops oute of their miſerye, and dydde muche good vnto them. After hym reigned Iuſtinianus his ſuſters ſonne, which was ſo righteous, that he compiled &amp; ſet in order all the inſtitucions of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours of rome, whiche nowe we name themperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all lawes, he buylded diuers goodly churches at co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtantinople, and gaue them greate riches, yearelye fode and ſuſtinaunce.<note place="margin">The begyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng of the popes ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</note> And by this meane the byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and preiſtes became ſomewhat more welthye then they were before.</p>
               <p>ANno. v<hi rend="sup">c</hi> .lxxx. was Gregorius Magnus (the firſt of that name) made byſhop of rome, and one named Mauricius de Cappadocia (y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt that came out of grecia) emperour when (as before) the byſhop of rome was become ſomewhat myghty and riche, they coulde not agree betwene them: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomoche
<pb facs="tcp:9430:9"/>
that Mauricius became ennemy vnto Gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gorye: At the ſame tyme, were the byſhoppes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge yet perſecuted, as yet being faithfull. And themperour continuyng in perſecution of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, god permitted a plage to come ouer hym, that he was takyn priſoner by Phoca, that was choſen emperour in hys rome, and cauſyd hym to be headyd.</p>
               <p>When nowe Phocas. Anno. vi<hi rend="sup">c</hi>. &amp; iii. kept hys ſeate at Conſtantinopell, And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> occidental empire (that is, Rome, Italy, France, and Germanie) were withoute a heade,<note place="margin">Practiſe to get londes and people</note> the vice emperoure beinge ſlaine of the Gottiſhe kinge Theodorico. The byſhop of Rome thoughte in his mynd, what &amp; yf thou hadſte the dominion of the vice Emperowre, that rowme neded not to ſtond open for a preye to euerye man? For that cauſe wente Bonifacius the thirde vnto themperour Phoca, to obteyne of hym, that as in worldly dominion euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> toke themperoure for the chief heade of all the worlde, lykewyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byſhop of Rome might be the chief biſhop within Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome. Then muſte nedes followe that he muſt haue landes and men.</p>
               <p>WHyles themperowre of Rome, kepte his ſeate at Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantinople, the byſhop of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantinople wrote hym ſelfe the chiefe biſhop, bicauſe of the empire. Thys ſhrodely troubled y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byſhop of Rome called Bonifacius,<note place="margin">when and i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops time this name papa bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> who went for the ſame cauſe to themperoure Phoca, praienge hym inſtantlye to graunte to the ſeat of Rome hys Imperialle priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henceforth to be a biſhop aboue al biſhops,
<pb facs="tcp:9430:10"/>
that is <hi>Papa patrum.</hi> And the byſhoprike of Rome to be named the chiefe of all biſhoprikes.</p>
               <p>ALthoughe this priuilege wolde not ſo lyghtly be graunted, yet he obteined it by continuall ſeute and begging. This will they not be a knowen of nowe, but ſaye that the pope is the ſupreme head and his romiſhe byſhoprike to be aboue all byſhop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rikes by goddes ordenaunce <hi>.xxi. Quamuis. and Diſtinct .xxii. omnes.</hi> And themperour Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus (ſay they) ſholde lykewiſe haue giuen this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilege to be pope, and his biſſhoprike to be aboue al other which likewiſe appereth by their own <hi>Decret. Diſtinc .xcvi. Conſtantinus.</hi> They make of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilege, whatſoeuer they wil the whiles it is to their profite. And thus haue they writen it in their owne Decrees. Thence commith the name of the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lieſt father the pope. The ſame haue they afterward colored with Chriſt, his holy worde, and Peter. It ſholde haue hadde no lykeneſſe to truth elles.</p>
               <p>BVt how agre theſe thinges, Conſtantinus did graunte the priuilege, Gregorius the thirde broughte it to paſſe by Phoca. And afterward muſt Chriſt confirme the ſame. Haue the faithful olde biſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhops before Conſtantynes tyme bene ſo ignorante that they vnderſtode not the holy ſcriptures? then is it no maruail that they were perſecuted. Yf they had ſet forth them ſelues by tymes, with chriſtes wordes, they myghte haue bene in better caſe.</p>
               <p>YF they hadde ſuche power of chriſte, what ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded they to entreate and flatter the vngodlye
<pb facs="tcp:9430:10"/>
emperours for it? when chriſtus choſe Paule to be an apoſtle amonge the heithe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, he muſt nedes be it, went alſo, &amp; did as he was commaunded, neding ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther emperours nor kinges confirmacion to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued vntil ſuch time as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perour did hed him. After that ſorte was Paule made pope, and Petrus was crucified. Therfore hath it another me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng then the pope allegeth. And of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame wordes <hi>Tu es Petrus</hi> They haue made them a lawe contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the doctrine of chriſte and the Apoſtles, &amp; the lyues of faithfull byſhops.</p>
               <p>THe ſame Bonifacius the third, when he hadde begged the chief byſhoprike of Phoca, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after he wrote him ſelfe pope Bonifacius the thirde of that name. He gathered al his biſhops &amp; preiſtes togither, and kept a concile at Rome. And declared there openly that from that time forward a pope beinge choſen by the prieſthode &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people, ſhuld be taken of aſmuch authorite, as if he were created by themperour &amp; admitted. Lo there may we ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt thankes or reward y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the pope gaue to themperour for the priuilege graunted vnto him takyng away from him his old rightes which were &amp; had ben themperours, ſince y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt chriſten empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour was. That the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perour ſhuld make no more byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope, &amp; ſo ſhuld y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byſſhops lykewiſe be more obedient to the pope the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to themperour, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpetch al their matter at Conſtantinople w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour. And thus began he priuily to rule &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his maiſter themperour, of whom he hadde begged the priuilege. The ſame was not done immediatly
<pb facs="tcp:9430:11"/>
by rigeur, but the pope ſuffred themperour to haue ſtyl for a time his deputie at Rome, which admitted the pope.</p>
               <p>NOwe was it come to ſuche a point, that the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes power wolde breake out, and take vppon hym to be aboue themperoure. And therfore, when after the birth of Chriſte .vii<hi rend="sup">c</hi>. &amp; .xviii. yeares Leo the third of that name, beinge emperoure, dyd put downe Germanum a Patriarche at Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantinople, and in his place ſet Anaſtaſium. The pope of Rome ſent Gregory the third vnto themperoure, &amp; wrote vnto him, that he ſhuld putte Germanum into his place againe, whiche themperoure wolde not do. There beganne all the miſcheife at ones. The pope found the meanes that all Italy fel from thempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and forſoke him (whiche none other pope hath done, but they paciently ſuffered perſecution) he cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed alſo themperour. Thinking whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thempire were deuided within it ſelfe, he wold be emperour, for he had alredy gotten him a greate name, amonge the princes and gouernours. Reaſon wold alſo require that he were not only the cheifhead by name, but al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo in might and power, and ſo wolde he kepe Rome and graunt thempire to whom he wolde and liſted.</p>
               <p>WHen now Conſtantinus the fifte, the ſonne of Leo the thirde was emperoure, and ſomwhat offended with the pope zacharia, by reaſon of his fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, whome Gregorius ſuffered to dye vnder his curſe in Meſſambria, and cauſed all Italye to fall awaye from him. He purpoſed to haue brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9430:11"/>
againe vnder his ſubiection. zacharius the pope fearing leaſte Conſtantinus might ſhorten his win<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges againe, ſoughte another maner of meane, then <hi>ſuper hanc petram,</hi> vpon this rocke, that is to ſaye,<note place="margin">Howe the pope came by rome.</note> him ſelfe. He ſent for helpe vnto Pipinus thadmini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtratour of fraunce, promiſinge to make him kynge of Fraunce, with the fauoure and good will of the Magiſtrates and rulers. Was not this lykewiſe done in deſpite of themperoure? And thus was the romiſhe empire deuided, one toke here, and another there. The pope kept Rome as his owne.</p>
               <p>HEre haue you the firſt kinge made by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> popes power, and the fauour of the rulers and gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nours, accordinge to the tenoure of his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall lawes <hi>.xi. q. i. Te quidem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pipinus the firſte kyng made by pope za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note> But this pope dyed the nexte yeare after, and Stephanus the ſeconde came in his ſtede, The whiche hadde muche ſorowe and trouble by kynge Aſtulphum, and likewiſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto Pipinus to aſſiſte the churche of Rome, Inſomuche that the kinge Pipinus toke his parte, and dyd driue kinge Aſtulphum awaye from rome, and gaue the pope Stephane Raue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nam, with dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other cities.</p>
               <p>ANd ſo is the pope ſucceſſiuely become a ruler aboue emperours and kynges, and al chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vniuerſallye. And hath forſaken y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the goſpell, the footeſteppes of the auncients pouertie, ſorrowe, care, and all other kyndes of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions and troubles &amp;c. Howe can he then be the mooſte holy vycare of chriſte, and ſucceſſor of ſainte
<pb facs="tcp:9430:12"/>
Peter? we fynde writen, Deare brethern be my fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, as I am the folower of chriſt .i. cor. xi. yf the pope with his company do folowe Chriſt, then is it reaſon that we lykewiſe followe him. But for their deuyliſh and abominable rule and doctrine, is ther not one iote in ſcripture. There is neither Peter, nor Paule that wyl know them, muche leſſe wil Chryſt hym ſelfe knowe them. Thus ſhal they be anſwered <hi>neſcio uos.</hi> I know you not. <hi>Quia operati eſtis ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> you haue ſet forth your own noughtynes in <hi>ſumma ebrietate ſicut fortes Ephraim.</hi> in all filthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and diuers other kyndes of vngodlynes (which be not to be wrytten) with the myght of this world.</p>
               <p>LO, hitherto haue you hadde in wryting the be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginninge of the pope, thaugme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tacion of his ſtate, and thirdly his full power and myght. Nowe ſhall you lykewyſe beholde and ſe the ſame in the olde painted figures folowynge.</p>
               <p>HOw be it many olde and faithful fathers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, and ſawe it well, yet durſte they not clearelye ſette it forthe, excepte only by fygures. Truſtyng alwais, that thorow the mercy of god a tyme ſhulde come when they myght be brought to lyghte. And ſo clearly ſette forth, that it were impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible more ſightlye to paint them. This wyll we now do for the plaiſure, and to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of ſuche as can not reade. To proue whether they be able to knowe a lyon by his clawes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:9430:12"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>The pope in his pontificall robes on euerye ſyde a beare, caſtynge them money in their mouthes, and the holy ghoſt a ſyde of hym. <figure>
                     <figDesc>scene with pope and bears</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this eſtate began the byſhop of Rome to ſette hym ſelfe. Anno .ccc.xi. at the tyme of Conſtantinus Magnus, the which when he had ouercome, Maxentiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> graunted the Chriſtianes to buyld churches, and gaue excedynge greate giftes towarde it but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther londes nor people, nor yet the cure of Rome, as they ſaye he dydde. When they ſmelled ryches, and daylye coueted more and more, then was
<pb facs="tcp:9430:13"/>
goddes worde laide aſide. And afterwarde ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came they all thinges (as they do yet) with monney Lordes, dukes, emperours, kinges, landes and peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple haue made ſubiect vnto them. They hadde well ſtudied the wordes of Philip the king of Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, where as he ſaithe, that there is no caſtell, no towne, ye no land, ſo ſtronge, which cannot be won, yf a moyle laden with money maye entre into it. And thus mony ouercommeth all thinges. And ſo haue they ſette a ſyde the very true rocke, which is Chriſte, the foteſteppes of Peter, and finally al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of tribulations and perſecutions. Their church haue they buylded vpon them ſelues, and therefore they may not endure or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue. They haue ſought alſo their helpe by the worldly powers, whiche the beares ſignifie and repreſent in this figure. Yf they had continued in their vocation, chriſte wold neuer haue forſaken them. But when they fell from it, and yet wolde (notwithſtandinge) maintaine all their doinges with theſe wordes, vpon this rocke. &amp;c. Chriſte went from them. And immediatly after thei ſoughte helpe, wherewith they yet continuallye (ye and againſte Chryſte hym ſelfe) wyll defende them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
               <p>And this fall of the byſhoppes firſte broke oute clearly, by pope zachariam, and Stephan the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d againſt Conſtantine the fifth, when they perſuaded Pipin the lieutenaunte of Fraunce to helpe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope againſte themperoure, and ſo doing, the pope wold make him kyng of Fraunce, Italy, and Germanye, with the fauoure and good wyll of the magiſtrates
<pb facs="tcp:9430:13"/>
and rulers.</p>
               <p>WHerwith defendeth the pope his church nowe with Chriſte or with beares? that is with worldlye powre and ſtrengthe. It hath tyghte well bene perceaued hitherto, and is as clere as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne. That the beares ſygnifie worldlye myght and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell people: We fynde it in the ſeconde booke of Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>muell, the ſeuententh chapter,<note place="margin">ii. Sam. 17.</note> where as Euſai repro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued the counſell of Ahitophell, Sayeng vnto Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolon, thou knoweſt thy father and his men, howe they be ſtronge, and they be chaſed in their myndes, and are euen as a beare robbed of her whelpes in the felde. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>IT ſuffiſeth not to ſaye, I am the chiefe byſſhop I haue the roume of an apoſtle, I ſytte in the Apoſtel ſtole, Petrus muſte preache, Paulus muſte alſo preache. Whyles the pope nowe followeth not Peter and Paule (the whiche he taketh for his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thores) in preachinge, teachinge, and feadinge of Chriſtes flocke, as the commaundement ſpecifieth, ſo ſytteth he beſides the apoſtell ſtole, and the ſpirit of god ſhrinkethe frome hym, the whiche more ſtren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gthened hym then al the beares of the world. But the chylde of perdicion with alſo his great tirannye (euen as Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das) muſt nedes be ſet forth and be knowen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:9430:14"/>
               <head>¶ The pope in his robes thruſteth downe the Aigle with the floure deliis at the ende of his ſlaffe. <figure/>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He crowned aigle doutles ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth themperour of Rome, whom the pope vnder the pretens of holines hath alwaies ſtopped with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> floure deliis, whiche is the frenſh kinge. And hathe robbed themperoure, of all maner of thinges, landes, and people, ſubſtance and riches, as aboue ſufficiently is declared. The pope fearing leſt in proces of time, the ſame thinges might be taken from him again, and that the righte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſe heire and lorde might fortune to recouer them againe (as often times hath bene ſeene by certayne
<pb facs="tcp:9430:14"/>
emperours). He wined him dailye more and more to other worldlye princes and rulers, &amp; reſiſted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, contrarie to all righte and reaſon. Neither was he ſo contented, but prouokinge likewiſe other to inuade themperoure. And by this meane he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained a ruler aboue them all. The ſame appea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red by Conſtantine the ſyxthe. For when zachari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the pope coulde not obtaine his purpoſe of him, he matched him ſelfe with Pipin, a lieutenaunte of fraunce, and made hym king therof. The ſame was a waye and meane to bring thempire vnto France. Is this any other thing, then with the aſſiſtence of the flowre deliis, to reſiſte themperoure? Ye, and vnto this preſent daie haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> popes alwaies more fauoured fraunce, then thempire. For what ſoeuer theſe two haue, hath bene in time paſt, vnder the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentalle empire. And to thentente it be not taken frome them againe, they ſtyke harde togither <hi>Et uiuit ex rapto, non hoſpes ad hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te tutus.</hi> That is. And the pope ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth by thinges robbed of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. But he that ſaith ſo now, is named an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike, and no where free.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Here kneleth the pope, and the hande of god threateneth and rebukethe hym, but a fox doth counſell the contrary?
<pb facs="tcp:9430:15"/>
                  <figure/>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the ſeconde boke of Moyſes the thirde chapter, god ſhewed vnto Moyſes oute of a fyrye buſſhe, what he ſhulde do. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo is here the hand of god pain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted in a buſſhe oueragainſt the pope, ſitting vpon his knees, threatning and rebuking the pope, bycauſe he doth vtterly applye him ſelfe to the riches &amp; dominion of this worlde, which is contrary to the vocation and nature of the apoſtolicall function. Suche threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges, admonitions, and warninges, haue manye yeres agone bene geuen to the pope, of manye and dyuers faithfull men. Ye, and thoughe certaine po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes faine wolde haue amended it. It coulde not be. For it were agreat abuſe to the church of rome: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wolde the foxeſſe ſuffre it to be done, that is to ſay, the Cardinalles, Notaries, and other of that ſee
<pb facs="tcp:9430:15"/>
the whiche euen at this preſent, pull backewardes, fearinge, that if the pope ſhulde followe Peter and Paule, their doctrine and lyfe, then muſt they like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe become poore. And that the foxes ſignifie ſuch as attaininge to the vnfaithfull princes and gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nours, the ſame ſhalte thou fynde. Luc. xiii. where as Chriſte calleth Herode themperours deputy at Ieruſalem a foxe.<note place="margin">Luc. xiii.</note> Whiles nowe the pope hearethe not the voice of god, he imagineth and practiſethe al waies and meanes, to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Aigle by the throte, that is to ſubdue, and bringe themperour vnder his power and dominion,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The pope hath the Aigle by the throte, and foy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth at the other byrdes lykewyſe with hys threforked ſcepter, and the ſame affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a monke to be agreable to ſcripture. <figure/>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9430:16"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen a man is taken by the throte, then muſt he nedes do what ſoeuer his aduerſary requirethe: Howe longe, and what maner of practiſe &amp; ſutteltie the pope hath vſed vntyll ſuche tyme as he had gotten them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire vnder his ſubieccion, is not neceſſarie here to be written, ſeing it is mencioned before. But this is ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry neceſſarye to be knowen, after what ſorte he han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled themperoure, when he toke thaigle by the throte? In the time of Iohan the .xii. and Otto the firſte there was ſtablyſhed a greuouſe intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, hurtefull and exitiable othe to all thempire, to be ſworne of all emperours,<note place="margin">The oth of themperor to the pope</note> in this maner. I Otto the good, promyſe and ſwere vnto the pope Iohn, my ſoueraine lorde, by the father, ſonne, and holy goſte. &amp;c. That (if I come to the citye of rome) I ſhal exalt and promote the holy churche of rome, and the, as ruler of the ſame, to my power and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. And farthermore that thou ſhalt loſe no parte of thy liuinge nor dignitie, whiche thou haſte with my will, counſell or aſſente. And within the citie of rome nothing to command or inſtitute (concerning thinges belonging vnto you, or the Romains) with out thy counſel. And all the londes longinge to ſ. Peter (ſo that they come vnder oure iuriſdiction) to reſtore vnto you. And whome ſoeuer I permytte to the gouernaunce of Italye, hym will I lykewiſe bynde by his othe to be aſſiſtente vnto you, and a defender of the Landes and poſſeſſions of ſainte Peter to his power.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9430:16"/>THe pope had the power to ſtablyſhe and ſette forthe this othe, by the auctorite (and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the tenoure) of his ſpirituall lawe <hi>.xii. q.i. clericus.</hi> is this any better, then takinge the Ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle by the throte? Thus became Otto the firſt em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of Germany with al his ſucceſſors very bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. And the moſte richeſt &amp; alſo myghtyeſt empire and kyngedome of all the worlde, was in bondage, and remained vnder the popes power, &amp; dominion.</p>
               <p>THus is the temporall gouernaunce euen here ouerthrowen. The popes before were ſeruaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, and themperoure a prince and gouernour ouer all thempire. Nowe is the pope become the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure ouer all, and themperoure a ſeruaunt, In ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche that he muſt kyſſe the fete of his ſubiecte. A faithfull and true Germaine emperoure oughte ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to graunt to be torne in peces. But doutles, if he dyd well beginne it, wel ſholde come of it. Fye of ſoche ſhame before god and the worlde, for this kna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uery can w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no maner of ſcripture be proued, except onely by their owne deuilyſſhe and vngodly lawes, whiche the mounke ſtandinge here by the pope con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth. Ye and to be euen as true as the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>WHen a right natural Germain hart reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breth wel this ſtinking pride and preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the pope, it is for anger lyke to burſt a ſunder, that the valeante and myghtie Germaine emperours haue ſuffred them ſelues to be made ſuch fooles &amp; ieſting ſtockes, as to kyſſe the feete of ſo vngodlye a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. I beleue that if it were not to vyle a thynge,
<pb facs="tcp:9430:17"/>
they muſte haue kyſſed the popes hindermoſt part. And yet euery man may not come ſo nyghe to the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly father.</p>
               <p>AT the firſte was it not ſo, Conſtantinus y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt and all his ſucceſſors (as many as were Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianes) made and choſe byſhops at rome and euery where. Nowe make the popes, emperours, kynges and byſhops, and therefore foineth he lykewiſe with his ſcepter at the other byrdes,</p>
               <p>WHyles nowe the pope takethe vpon hym the gouernaunce and rule of this world, ſo muſt he lykewiſe promiſe and ſwere to the hygheſt prince of this worlde, whiche is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll. And the ſame declareth the figure nexte following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Here commeth the Deuyll with the pope and giueth hym his commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dements, accordinge to whiche he muſt behaue hym ſelfe in thys hys king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in earth.
<pb facs="tcp:9430:17"/>
                  <figure/>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hyles (as aboue is mencioned) by the forſakinge of goddes worde, the perſuaſion and illuſion of the deuyll, whiche onelye is a prynce of this worlde) the popes be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſucceſſours, and deputies vnto hym, as their cheife gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure here in earthe. So haue they nothinge more to do with god, Chriſte nor his doctrine. For Chriſt ſaith. Ioh. xiiii. The prince of this world commeth and hath nothinge in me, and ſo ſhall nowe (whiles I am here) the prynce of the worlde be thruſte oute. Iohan. xii. Thus can the pope haue no parte with Chriſte, concerninge the kyngedome of this worlde, whyles his chiefe miniſter the deuyll hathe nothinge in hym.<note place="margin">Math. 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> Howe can they now defend the patrimonie and poſſeſſion (as they name it) of
<pb facs="tcp:9430:18"/>
Chriſte and Pieter?<note place="margin">Math. 8. c. Luc. 9. f.</note> Chriſtus hadde not where to lay his head in. And Peter forſoke his poore fiſher bote, with his patched fiſhernet alſo.</p>
               <p>CHriſte ſought not in this worlde (as many co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous parſons do, the which gather and heap great ſubſtance togither, neither dare they ſpend it them ſelues, to the ende that they might leue muche behinde them for their executours) but was ſente frome his father to teache and ſuffre perſecution, which he fulfilled. Euen the very ſame left he to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be his ſeruauntes,<note place="margin">Mat. 10. b. Luc. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> for a teſtament, ſayenge, I ſende you forth, as my father hath ſent me, as ſhepe among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wolues, yf they perſecuted me,<note place="margin">Ioh. 13.15</note> they ſhall lykewiſe do the ſame vnto you, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruaunt is no greater then his lorde. Here fynde we very lyttle of the kyngdome of this worlde.</p>
               <p>ANd thus is all the popes boaſte and preſump<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion nothing worthe. For he is none of the chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren of Abraham, (Howe be it, he wryteth and ſayth hym ſelfe to be the folower of Chriſt) but a childe of the deuill, whiche fathers wordes and workes he foloweth diligently alwaies. And the ſame verifieth his owne doctrine and lyfe, forbidding meates, ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and wedlocke, to maintaine horedome, with more other abuſes whiche be not to be ſpoken.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Io. 8. d. 10 a 13. e. 1. Ioa. 4.</note>HE that hearethe goddes wordes, and dothe therafter, is of god. But whoſoeuer hearethe them not, is not of god. Then muſt he nedes be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9430:18"/>
deuyll, which is alſo a father, but of lyes,<note place="margin">Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. a. Ioh. 8. d. 1. Ioh. 3. b.</note> And who ſo euer followeth hym, goethe about with lyes.</p>
               <p>THe deuill is the prince of this worlde. And the pope writeth him ſelfe alſo a gouernoure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, as hauynge receaued the ſame of him that had power to delyuer it. The deuyll from the begin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ninge hathe bene a murderer and lyer, and the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thore and father of all lyes. The ſame chargeth he like wiſe his officers and ſeruauntes withall, for he wolde gyue them nothinge, doinge not his will. Euen ſo is all that longeth to the pope, nothinge but murther, lies, and deceite, <hi>Ita patrem ſequitur ſua proles.</hi> No crowe becommeth white with waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhinge. There is nowe both Criſame and baptyme loſte. And therfore will the lorde ſubuerte and ouerthrowe them, as it is (laudes and praiſe vnto god) begon alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, yet they thinke ſtyll, euen as they gotte it, euen ſo to kepe it. As is to be ſeene in the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:9430:19"/>
               <head>¶The pope thruſtethe the lambe thorowe with his ſworde. And therefore gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him the deuyll the keyes that is, power and might. <figure/>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Owe be it the pope boaſteth &amp; day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye cryeth, his keyes to be of Chriſt, though it be nothinge ſo. The olde fathers perceaued the ſame righte wel, and therfore haue they painted here the deuil with the keyes by the pope. Becauſe that all the auctoritie whiche he hath here in earthe, commeth not from god, but from the deuyll. For howe coulde the power of god be with the ſworde that kylleth the lambe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9430:19"/>THe deuill is the father, and the pope the ſonne The deuill is a prince of this worlde, and the ſame hath he geuen vnto the pope, as his heyre, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all maner of worldly might and power, the ſame ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifie the keyes, the rodde, and the ſworde. And who ſoeuer obeyeth him not in this his power and dignite, the ſame doth he ſcourge firſt with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rodde admoniſheth him, and curſeth. &amp;c. And yf that wyll not helpe, then muſte he dye with hys ſworde as an heretike. The ſworde of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite whiche Paule ſpeakethe of, oughte rather to procede out of the popes mouth,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6. Hebre. 4.</note> yf he wold be named the ſucceſſoure of Peter.</p>
               <p>But euen ſuche a mannes ſeruaunte as he is, ſuch kinde of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery weareth he. And the ſame ſhewethe the figure fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowinge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>The pope with his keyes, them kepeth a ſerpente, in his pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificall robes and treaſor ful of ducates, and the power la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be is the harde cote of.
<pb facs="tcp:9430:20"/>
                  <figure/>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He deuyll is the wylye ſerpente, the which yet ſtill by wilynes auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceth the popes power, ruleth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame and kepeth in ſtrength. Inſomuch that by that meane, he hath almoſt ſubdued, and broughte vnder his dominion all Chriſtendome, ſome he ſeduceth, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mony, &amp; ſo be his ornamentes full of ducates, ſome againe with his falſe and fained ypocriſye, hauynge a croſſe in his handes. Some by might and power, So that partly by the ſence of the croſſe and keies, and partely by the deuill and Fraunce he ſubdueth altogether. And it goeth with the pope, euen as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poca .xiii. is writen: That as many as will not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp hym, ſhalbe kylled. And all his men be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,
<pb facs="tcp:9430:20"/>
ſo that no man dare by or ſell, ſaue he that hath the marke in his righthande or in his foreheade.<note place="margin">The poeps marke.</note> There falleth the lambe euen to the grounde. The pope headeth him, and he muſte dye. In all theſe doinges he hathe kepte hym ſelfe with the kocke, that is Fraunce, ſignified by the kocke, whiche hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth him to ſuppreſſe goddes worde. And all this vnder a pretence of fained holines. So hathe he obteyned the rule both in ſpiritualle and temporalle matters ouer all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome. And with the aſſiſtence of his wolues he trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vnde his fete all rulers &amp; gouernours that they can go no farther then he permitteth them. As the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure folowinge declareth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The pope ſtandeth vpon the emperiall crowne hauynge a raſoure in his hande, and the wolfe the ſworde.
<pb facs="tcp:9430:21"/>
                  <figure/>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O be a foteſtole, is ouer all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world a vyle and abiecte thinge. Neither myghte themperoure come to a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer degree, then that he and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worldly rulers,<note place="margin">Pſal. 109. Math. 22. d Marc. 12. d. Actu 2. d. 1. Cor. 15. c. Heb. 1. b. 10.</note> muſte lye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the popes fete. Dauid coulde write no greater honour vnto Chriſt in the Pſalter, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that his enemies ſhuld become a foteſtole vnto hym. And ſo was it the moſt paine and ſpite to the ennemyes to ly vnder the fete of him that ouercame them. Thoſe that be ouercome muſte do vnto the conquerer, what ſoeuer he wyll. And ſo ruleth nowe the pope themperialle crowne euin as he will, and hath laid it vnder his fete that is, vnder his power. And hathe ſo vtterly ſubdued the ſame, that it is
<pb facs="tcp:9430:21"/>
more to be lamented, then largely deſcribed.</p>
               <p>IT was not ynoughe that the pope hadde ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thempire both of landes &amp; goodes. But he muſte alſo haue the ſworde withall.<note place="margin">Sap. 6. a Ro. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.4. c rom. 13. a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 3. 1 Pet. 2. b.</note> To thend that euen as the ſworde appertaineth to the highe powers hauinge landes and people, for the wealth of the good, and puniſhment of the euill. He might lykewiſe defende and kepe all whatſoeuer he had taken from thempire. Neither is it againſt raiſon. For a wolfe is a tiranne beaſt,<note place="margin">3. reg. 13 u Iud. 8. c Deut. 13 a Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. b 1. Ioh. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſpecially amonge ſhepe, And therefore muſte he alſo haue weapons to playe the butcher and murderer withall but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly amonge the chriſtianes, farther dare he not ſwel. Concerninge theſe raueninge wolues hath Chriſt and his apoſtles left many warninges behind them to teache vs to beware of them. But the popes ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoure is ſo ſharpe, that before a man can loke behind hym, (ye and ſcarſſe feleth it) he is wounded with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> popes miſcheif, wickednes, and vngracyouſnes. And the ſame ſignifieth the raſour.<note place="margin">Pſal 52. a</note> Pſal. lii.</p>
               <p>THerfore nowe,<note place="margin">Dan. 11. e. Iſai. 11. 2. Teſſa. 2. 1. Ioh. 2.</note> ſeinge the pope hath ſette hys ſeate aboue bothe ſpirituall and temporal po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, ye and entreth into the iudgementes of god, rulynge the conſciences of men. And ſoche as heare hym not, he punyſheth with the blody ſword. Chriſt thorowe his promiſe and the glory of his name, wil ſuffer it no longer, but hathe alreadye thruſte hym awaye from hym, as the figure folowinge ſheweth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:9430:22"/>
               <head>The angell taketh the keyes from the pope, but yet he remayneth prowde in hys power <figure/>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A. reg. 13. c. A. reg. 15 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. reg. 16. c <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. reg. 28.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere it goeth to work with the pope as it did with Saule, whiche was putte downe by god, and another annointed kinge before he was all togither putte oute of his dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Saul thought foraſmoch as the prophete had annointed him kyng by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demente of god, that he mighte do what ſoeuer he wolde, ye and by the lawe. Soche pryde and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience ſuffred god for a tyme.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. reg. 31. a. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. par. 11. a</note> But it was not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardide with a meane deathe, for he kylled hym
<pb facs="tcp:9430:22"/>
ſelfe in deſpeare. And ſo the pope now,<note place="margin">Iudi. 9. v.</note> beinge nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ordened of God, Chriſte nor his Apoſtles, and thinkinge quietlye to lyue the whyles he hath, hathe broughte all thinges vnder him, ſo ſendethe god an Angell whiche pullethe awaye the lions ſkinne frome the aſſe, and makethe him a mockinge ſtocke to all the worlde with his holye woorde. In ſomoch that he knowith not nowe which way to go oute or in. And althoughe he be ſuppreſſid of God, yet, wyll he not ſhrinke or abaſh, but kepith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rodde ſtill in his hande, therwith to ſubdue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſciences of men, &amp; remaineth pufte vp as a todde or a bolde pecocke in his pryde by certaine people. Whiche to mainteyne againſte the wyll of god,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. reg 28. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Liui. 20. b. Deut. 8. b. Detu. 16 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth counſil (as Saul did by the Phytoniſſa) not by God but by the deuyll, and by all the deuylyſhe people and tyrannes of this worlde. Therfore is he ſet forthe in the figure folowing withoute any croſſe, and his boke ſhytte vp, and ſette aboute with beares.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The pope ſette aboute with beares.
<pb facs="tcp:9430:23"/>
                  <figure/>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He popes holynes wyl now almoſt come to lyght. And it is ſo farre gone with hym, that he ſaith, yf no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge helpe me ſo helpe me the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll and all his houſholde. It was not vnknowen vnto hym, that he mighte not defende him ſelfe with the holye ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whiche is directly againſte hym, and therfore hath he ſhytte his boke and taken it to him ſelf. Commaundynge vpon great paines and the curſe, no man to reade in it, leſte men ſhulde perceiue that his dignitie coulde not be proued by the ſame. And hathe ſette him ſelfe amonge the beares before and behinde, aboue and beneth, that is, with myghtye
<pb facs="tcp:9430:23"/>
prynces and men of warres, whiche helpe hym to maintaine his dignitie, to the ende that thys boke, with alſo his power be not taken away from hym.</p>
               <p>HAth not all this tyranely anoughe continued almoſt theſe thirtye yeares? Let them ſuffre more that lyſte. Neither is it come to an ende yet, god helpe vs. And yet wyl (notwithſtandyng) theſe beares, bloudſuppers, and murderers, be the mooſt Chriſtianes. Theſe beares nede no farther expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for we ſee daily before oure eyes what &amp; which they be. Neither is it greatly neceſſary to recite the great pitie, in wyddowes, fatherles and motherles children, the deſtruction and murder of the people. For it is al cleare, as the ſonne. The ſonne hath not yet clearly lycte vp the bloude of the innocent Abel neither hath the earthe dronke it in: O god, in thy kyngedome hathe the bloud of an Innocente man called vengeaunce vpon Cayne the fyrſt murderer. Howe can the innocentes bloude holde his peace, ſo longe? when the tyrantes haue bathed them ſelfes almoſt to the very kne in bloud, neither thinke they as yet to hold vp. Here neded well an Helias, which thorowe the worde of the lorde ſpake to kyng Ahab in Iſraell.<note place="margin">3. reg. 11. 2. reg. 12.</note> Thou haſt killed and taken poſſeſſion of Naboths vineyarde. Therfore in the place where the dogges lycked the bloode of Naboth, there ſhal the dogges lycke euen thy bloude alſo, &amp;c. But it ſemeth (parauenture) vnto the righteouſe and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull god, as yet to be no tyme. willynge his people to learne to be the more paciente,<note place="margin">Pſal. 9</note> vntyll the pytte be dygged vp for the vngodly. Pſal. xciiii. when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9430:24"/>
power of the Tiphones ones ſhalbe gathered togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euen as Pharao,<note place="margin">As theſe gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>auntes cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Tipho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes (throughe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce they had in their greate ſtature) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quire the heauens, ſo dyd Pharo the chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſraell, through the truſt he had in his great multitude.</note> then ſhall it be ſodenly done with them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ An vnicorne thruſteth the popes crowne from his heade. <figure/>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Owe be it the pope with his owne falſeheade and ſubteltie hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the reigne of this worlde by the deuyll (for no chriſtian euer helped another to ſuche a kyngdome) he, kepeth him ſelf therin, And though god haue putte him downe, he wil not yet auoide, yet ſhal the righteouſenes of god come and iudge, and euen vtterlye deſtroye the pope, and expel and
<pb facs="tcp:9430:24"/>
driue hym out of his reigne, which is the deuylles, by whome he gotte it, with worldly power. And the ſame ſignifieth the vnicorne,</p>
               <p>LEt no Chriſtiane be greued thoughe the pope and other tyrannes do yet ſticke to their domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion before the face of the world. Be it ſufficient vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to him to know the iudgement of god, and that the pope muſte ſo longe remaine and walke in the ſame ſtate and lyfe, vntyll he happen ones ſodenlye to come vnder the gallowes, And than muſt he hange without redemption.</p>
               <p>ALthough the keyes, that is the power of abſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lucion, is taken away from the pope, yet is he ſette here in ſpyte of all faithfull perſonnes, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyue ſynne, vntyll ſuche tyme as the zodomiticall ſynne be accompliſſhed. And then will god (euen as he did ſend to the Iewes a Titum) ſende a Iehu to Baales preiſtes, and ſuffre them,<note place="margin">3. re. 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 4. re. 9. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> one to deſtroye another.</p>
               <p>BVt that the pope ſhoulde and muſte be putte downe from a great dignitie and power. And (the whiles he hathe the deuyll the prince of this worlde to aſſiſt hym on his ſyde) can not ſo ſoone be done as we meane, ſo muſt his enemies be as ſtrong as vnicornes.</p>
               <p>DAVYD calleth vnto the God. Pſalm .xxii. Delyuer me frome the vnicornes.<note place="margin">Pſal. xxii. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> By them he meaneth doutles his myghty and ſtronge enemyes of the whiche he fearethe that he ſhall in no wiſe be
<pb facs="tcp:9430:25"/>
delyuered, except god helped him, as namely, was Saule with his company. Lykewiſe the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of Chriſte be named in this Pſalme vnicor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, by reaſon of their tirannye, wherein they were lyke to the kynde and nature of the vnicorne. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of writeth Iob lykewiſe. cap. xxxix. Thinkeſte thou that the vnicorne wilbe ſo tame as to do the ſeruice?<note place="margin">Iob. 39.</note> or to abyde ſtyll by thy cryble? Canſte thou bynde the yoke aboute an vnicorne in thy forow, to make hym plowe after the in the valeis? maieſt thou truſt hym (bycauſe he is ſtronge) or commyt thy laboure vnto hym, that he wyll brynge home thy corne, or to cary any thinge to thy barne? In no wiſe. For it is to excedynge ſtronge, fearfull and vnruely a beaſt.</p>
               <p>THe very true horne of ſaluacion that ſhal ouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>throw all vngodlynes (yf thou wylte ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allye vnderſtande it) zacharias reciteth.<note place="margin">Luce. 1.</note> Luc. i. And what ſoeuer god hath ſpiritually, that is, ordeyned by hym ſelfe, that muſt alwayes procede in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world There can he well fynd an aſſure when his plaiſure is, and afterwarde breake the rodde alſo, and caſt it into the fyre.</p>
               <p>Seynge the pope wyll haue it ſo, that no man ſhalbe able to reſiſte his power, So muſte there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des come a more puiſſant and mightier than he that ſhall lyft him out of his neſte, that muſt he nedes a byde, and muſt periſh in the meane tyme, let him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende him well.<note place="margin">Mat. 3.17. luce. 3. Apo. 18.</note> For then is all loſt. The axe is put vnto the roote of the tree and the workeman ſtry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth alreadye therein, to pul out his roote from the
<pb facs="tcp:9430:25"/>
grounde, in ſomuch that men ſhall aſke,<note place="margin">Apo. 18.</note> where dyd Babylon the great citie ſtande?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶By the pope lyeth a ſtronge oxe pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge, and the worldly gouernours beholde it ſtyll. <figure/>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the .xxii.<note place="margin">Pſa. 22.</note> Pſalme complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethe Dauid vnto god ſaieng, manye Oxen are come aboute me, and fatte bulles cloſe me in on euery ſyde. There ſignifye the bulles and oxen, doubteles, the ſtronge enemyes of Dauid
<pb facs="tcp:9430:26"/>
the kynge Saule with his adherentes. But ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally it appartaineth vnto the death and paſſion of Chriſt, theſe twaine haue thorowe the helpe of god ouercome all their enemies, as hauinge righte, the pope as hauynge no right. The whiche hath almoſt brought vnder him all princes, landes, cities, and people, for all theſe muſte lye downe at the popes fete and kyſſe them deuoutly wiſſhing neuertheles to be diſamiſt of it, if poſſible were.</p>
               <p>SEcondarely is lykewiſe this Oxe compared to the common poore artificer and huſband man. Seinge the Oxe is a common rude beaſte, and apt to all rude and hard laboures, in the feldes and vil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lages, but ſelden in the greate cities, fedde with no delicate meates, but onely with heye and chapped ſtrawe. &amp;c. And is by the popes vngodly and tiran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe inſtitutes ſo farre conſumed, that he can no more pul or drawe, and ſo ſore ſucked out (ye the ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry marye out of his bones) that he is no more able to ſtonde, but lyeth there, wiſhinge delyueraunce of the popes tyrannye, but all in vayne, for ſuche as ſhulde helpe therin, ſtand ſtyll and loke vpon it. And euery one putteth from hym, as if it appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not vnto hym.</p>
               <p>By raiſon ought emperours, kinges, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces here to putte to their handes, and to helpe the poore oxe out of his miſerye, and ſo mighte their owne buſines likewiſe proſper the better afterward And the ſubiectes ſhoulde become the more obedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.
<pb facs="tcp:9430:26"/>
For the holy goſpell hath taughte them how they ſhall behaue them ſelues towarde the poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and rulers, ye and they wold dowtles do it. But in the reuelacion may we ſone ſee, what they be that worſhip the beaſte.<note place="margin">Apo. 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> And then ſhall we haue the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and cauſe why it happeneth not. And therfore becommeth of the paciente oxe a grimminge beare, as ſhewethe the figure folowinge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Falleth on the pope a griminge beare with her whelpes. <figure/>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9430:27"/>WHyles nowe the pope and his adhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rentes euen at this preſent day wil not retourne vnto the right waye, it is no maruell though euery man be vnwillynge, and both the Oxen and alſo calues become beares. And is to be feared that if they wyll ſo procede withoute better hede, that at the laſte littell goodnes wyll come of it.<note place="margin">Anno .xxv. was there an inſurrec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betwene the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le of germa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny and the ſpirytual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note> Fewe remembre nowe that which moſte pitiouſely chaunced. Anno .xxv. God ſaue vs from ſoche another fall. I feare me that if it ſhulde ones againe come to ſuche a pointe, the beare with her whelpes wolde otherwiſe vſe them ſelues, and to earneſtly ſet them to worke. But here from wyll god preſerue his people, &amp; for al that drowne Pharao in the reade ſeas neuertheles. what is it, of a longe tyme, with greate pompe and pryde (other abominaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons I ſpeake not of) to kepe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, or parlyamentes, for the worde of god? God the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of vs all hath not ſo gloriouſelye ſet forthe his actes, with ſhepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdes and fiſhers kept he his coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cels, &amp; breif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fyny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed his matters. But truelye euen as we mind it, euen ſo doth Chriſt auaunce it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:9430:27"/>
               <head>¶A foxe runneth awaye with the popes banner. <figure/>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>E and rather than the pope ſhulde paſſe vndeſtroyed, his owne famy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye or houſeholde ſhoulde rather do it. The ſame ſignifieth the foxe. Before he ſwaded hym from god, and nowe ſeing the pope can reigne no lenger, he departeth from him euen as a maiſter of a hundreth craftes, as he boaſteth hym ſelfe to be in Eſopo. againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> catte which had but one thinge to helpe her wythall, but when the hounter came with his dogges behynd them bothe, the ſymple cat
<pb facs="tcp:9430:28"/>
ranne vpon a tree, and the ſuttel foxe paide for all with his ſkinne. Euen ſo feareth here the popes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mili lykewiſe, in manye matters haue they ben hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto good enoughe, but nowe in tyme of nede, to kepe them in their neſtes, they can do nothinge. Therfore they runne awaye with ſhame frome the poope, with goodes and ſubſtaunce, whiche they haue gotten from hym with their ſuttelties and falſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hed, and thus muſt he ſtand alone. Neither is it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficient vnto them, to runne awaye from him them ſelues, but moreouer take alſo with them, all that longethe vnto hym, hys poſſeſſyons, honoure, and myghte, that is, they can no more helpe him w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his decrees, for the godly ſcripture is againſt them and to ſtronge for them. And ſo do both the foxes, &amp; myghte and power runne togither away. Here may the pope rightwell thinke on the poet, where he ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth. <hi>Donec eris foelix multos numerabis amicos. Tempora ſi fuerunt nubila, ſolus eris.</hi> When it was well with me, then hadde I manye frendes, but in myne aduerſitie they be all fled awaye. But truelye the rewarde is but reaſonable. Soche as haue clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed ſaint Peter, be moſt worthye to ſpoile him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. With craft and ſutteltie didde the poperye fyrſt come vp, and with the ſame muſt it come down againe, to the ende that the ſalte might retourne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, wheras it was before, to the water. Therfore he ſitteth nowe naked and bare vppon his pardon cheſte, as a ieſting ſtocke to all men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:9430:28"/>
               <head>☞The pope ſitteth here naked vpon his pardon chyſte, the huſbandman mocketh hym ſayeng, his foly to be right well knowen to euery man. <figure/>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Smuche as we haue written hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto haue we ſene in our tyme, but nowe reſteth this onely, that he ſytteth not naked. But yf we ſpeake according to the holy ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, we ſhall lykewiſe fynd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame prophecie to be on a good way toward. In diuers places in the holy ſcripture is mencyoned, howe god hathe dyſcouered Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma and Gomorra, Iheruſalem, and more other
<pb facs="tcp:9430:29"/>
landes, and made them mockynge ſtockes to al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and at laſt made them naked altogether. Ezechielis xvi. ſpeaketh god in this maner, I wyll gather to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither all thyne enemyes againſt the, and wyll dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer thy ſhame before them, that they maye ſee thy fylthynes. I wyll geue the ouer into their power that they ſtrype the out of thy clothes. All thy faire and beautifull Iewels ſhall they take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the. And ſo let the ſytte naked and beare. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>THeſe wordes with more other, witneſſe nothing elles, but that god will trouble their worldlye rule and power, and vtterly deſtroie it. So muſte this figure likewiſe be ſet forth here. That the pope at the laſt leſeth all hys power, honour, riches, plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure, hys coffers with monye, and finallye is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all comfort or aſſiſtence of all the worlde, and ſyttethe bare and naked, And is ſo much deſpyſed, that the verye huſbandman mocketh hym ſayeng. Lo what a goodly pope be you nowe? Lo what a ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler arte thou nowe aboue kynges and emperours? lo, where is thy godlynes? Lo where is thy pardon? Lo where is thy curſynge &amp; banninge? &amp;c. I thinke you be but poore nowe, I thinke you abyde honger and colde, we wyll handell you better yet, thou ſhalte be burnt in the fyre, euen as thou haſt meaſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red vnto other. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>To this ende muſte it come, and lette no man be abaſhed,<note place="margin">4. re. 24. &amp;. 25 2. Para. 36</note> thoughe it ſemyth otherwaies yet to be. The chyldren of Ieruſalem muſte nedes to Babel and there ſuffer out their tyme, But what followeth
<pb facs="tcp:9430:29"/>
vpon the ſame?<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſd. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.2.5. Hiere. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.52</note> when your tyme then ſhalbe accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſſhed, I wyll remembre you, viſite you againe, and miniſter my good worde vnto you, and brynge you home againe. And the landes of that kynge ſhalbe obediente to many kinges and people. And finally be brought vnder the Medianes. Haue we ben faine to ſuffre a while? and as yet be? the vngod lye be not ſhylde quyte of it, as if they were in the righte waye. But they ſhall paye twiſe for it, which they haue at once deuoured, as we fynde it to be hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pened vnto all the vngodlye Emperours, kynges, and princes, and high preiſtes, in the holy ſcripture</p>
               <p>THe ſame witneſſeth not only the holy ſcripture wherin they beleue but a lytell,<note place="margin">The prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy of Hylle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde.</note> but the prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye likewiſe of a certaine Nonne named Hillegard, beinge one of their owne marke, ſaieng. Al world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly princes and the common people alſo ſhal fierſely fall vpon you preiſtes, which hitherto haue abuſed me. They wyll turne you awaye from them, &amp; putte you to flyghte. They ſhall take awaye youre ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce and riches, becauſe that in youre tyme you haue not well kepte the ordre of youre preiſthode. Theſe wordes will they ſpeake by you. Let vs caſte out theſe othebreakers, robbers, and people reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhed of all iniquitie out of the holye catholicalle churche, for the holy churche is contaminated and polluted by them. And therfore will god ſuffer alſo ſuche thinges to come ouer you. And the kinges of the worlde ſhall aſſiſte them that ſhall auoide you with their earthly power, and myght. Your prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dignitie and annointinge wyl they exteme as no
<pb facs="tcp:9430:30"/>
thinge worthe, And ſo that propoſe wil they gather togither in counſell, that they may driue you out of their iuriſdictions, becauſe you haue driuen a waye the innocente lambe frome me with your moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly and habominable workes.</p>
               <p>THerefore wyll the heauens raine diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which ſhalbe againſt men, as a reuenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce of god. The miſt ſhall couer the whole earth, ſo that all your graſſe ſhall drye vp, and your orna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes become paile. The profunditie ſhall ſuſtre earthequakynge, and then ſhall appeare the verye anger of god, and ſmart bothe heauen and earth.</p>
               <p>GOd wyll ſende a righteouſe and ſtreighte iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement againſte the tranſgreſſours of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes. And then ſhall we ſaye altogether. Howe longe ſhall we forbeare and ſuffre theſe raueninge wolues? They oughte to be feaders of the ſoules, and they be deſtroyers of them. They bynd and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bynde (which nothinge longethe to them) at their owne pleaſure, and as mooſt fearefull beaſtes they vtterly caſt vs awaye. And thus remaine we ſtyl in oure, and they in their ſynnes, Inſomuche that all Chriſtendome periſheth thorowe them. And what ſoeuer is right that write they not, but onely it whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is contrary to the law. They deuour vs, as the wolfe deuoureth the ſhepe, they lyue ſtyll in luſte &amp; gloutenye, they be very robbers of the church. And what ſoeuer they cancome by, they take &amp; deuour it. They make vs alſo with their occupacion poore &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:9430:30"/>
beggarly. They dampne them ſelues and vs alſo.</p>
               <p>THerefore wyll we iudge them righteouſelye, and ſeparate them from vs, for they be rather ſaducers then teachers. &amp;c. yet care they not for it, and remaine ſo ſtyll, makynge all kyngdomes ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto them. For all this they muſte awaye, and leaue behynde them all that they haue, neither ſhall they afterwarde rule any more ouer the people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, with landes, poſſeſſions, vyneyardes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther temporall goodes, which the worldly princes be ſette for. A pope ſhulde be a pope, a knyghte, a knyght. A gentilman, a gentilman. And therefore ſhall be taken away from ſuch thinges as they poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſede vnrighteouſely, and not righteouſely. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>BVt againſte the ſame wyll rebelle the heades of this worlde, the ſpirituall people, as the pope cardinalles, byſhops, abbates and other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates. Fyrſte with their curſe, and wyth ſhyttinge vp of the heauens, but the ſame wyll men feare but a lytle,<note place="margin">An ende of the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye of the nonne Hille<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>garde.</note> after that wyll they gette them to theyr har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſhe and weapons, therewithe to defende them ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues. But againſte the iudgemente of God they can do nothynge, for their tyme is come. &amp;c. This pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied the nonne Hillegarde.</p>
               <p>So muſte nowe the bloudye hoore drynke of her chalys,<note place="margin">Dan. 7. b Mat 25. d. Apo. 19. d and .20. c</note> and the beaſte wyth alſo the falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phetes be caſte downe in the botthomleſſe pytte where as is no reſte, nighte nor daye, eternallye there to ſuffre paines. And then wyll Chryſt
<pb facs="tcp:9430:31"/>
raiſe vp faithfull ſhepe herdes to fede his flocke.</p>
               <p>WHat theſe ſhalbe, we fynde lykewiſe in the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptures openly enoughe declared, they that come from hym. And howe maye it faile in ſuche as god ſendeth? God is righteouſe, and ſendethe alſo whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſeeth his time, righteouſe ſhepeherdes. And they do righteouſely, for euen as they teache, euen ſo they lyue.</p>
               <p>ANd theſe be the true ſeruauntes whiche Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus ſpeaketh of,<note place="margin">Math. 24. d. and .25. b. Lu. 12. e. 19. b</note> the whiche in due tyme ſette forthe the giftes and glory of the father of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe holde, and not their owne tradicions, whiche as yet (god amende it) the whole worlde is full of. But god wyll nowe ſhortlye ſcume awaye all filthynes, and therevnto helpe Ieſus Chriſte. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <p>THere be dyuers ſuche other prophecies not ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſarye to be written here. I hope there wil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendement folowe after this, excepte they haue ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eyes nor eares: But whom wolde not this olde and true and faithfull declaration of the romiſhe &amp; Babylonyſhe bryde, bringe to conuerſion &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge? She is ſo clearely ſet forth and painted with all her falſehead and colours, that it coulde no lyue lyer be done. Hathe not ſhe with her chalice made dronke, and with her ſutteltie and deceite ouercome Emperours, kinges, princes and lordes? and with her ſnares ouerthrowen all Chriſtendome? Lette
<pb facs="tcp:9430:31"/>
euery man marke it well. When dyd they any other thinge, but powi and ſhaue, lye and deceiue, burne, banne, kepe warres and murder? vntyll ſoche tyme continually, as they were become the heades of al kingedomes. &amp;c. The ſame hath (as aboue is menci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oned) laſted manye yeares, but now will it take an ende. For the tyme of the hoore is come about.<note place="margin">Apo. 1. a. 21. a and .21. c Eſai. 41. a. &amp; 44. b. &amp;. 48. c</note> And he commeth that ſpeaketh in Apocalipſi. I am A. and O. the beginninge and the endinge, the firſte and the laſte, bleſſed be they that folowe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, to the ende that he maye come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tree of lyfe,<note place="margin">Apo 22. c. 2 a Gene. 2. b</note> and enter into the gates of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> celeſtial Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſhalbe excloſed al doggs enchaunters, hoores murdrers, Idolotrers, and al ſuche as loue and folowe lyes.</p>
               <p>SO hath nowe Ieſus Chriſte ſente his aungell againe to ſhewe the people that he is the verye roote of Dauid, and the cleare morning ſtarre.<note place="margin">Ap. 22. d. 2, d, Mat. 2. Luc. 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. cor 4 b 2. Pet. 1. d.</note> And in none other is there any ſaluacion, but in him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, for it is written.<note place="margin">Act 4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Math 1 c Philip. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> There is none other name vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the heauens, wherin we maye be ſaued, but this onelye. &amp;c. Now he that is faithfull, be he ſtill faith full. He that is holy, lette hym become more holyer, and continue to the ende, and let him not longe for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time approcheth. And thus let euery man be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, for he knocketh, &amp; if ye do open, wel and good. yf not, you knowe the daunger, both baptiſme and crifame is loſte on ſuch people, and thus Chriſte ſende vs all his holy ſpirite. Amen,</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9430:32"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt whether theſe or ſuche like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies be of god, and by the holye gooſte, or no, moueth not me. For as muche as I ſe, when god wyll ſhewe his diſpleaſure and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and will bringe to paſſe ſome great acte, that all creatures do prophecy before, &amp; geue warninge, although it helpe but litel. Euen ſo when he wolde ſubuerte Ieruſalem, his prophetes dyd prophecye it before, but it auailed not, Chriſte hadde threatened it vnto them. The apoſtles had warned them therof it preuailed not, They hearde voices in the Temple, They ſawe ſignes in the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they hearde battailes in the cloudes, madde men and ſuche as were out of their wittes, did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy it vnto them, but al theſe thinges preuailed not, they ſawe it in acte, it preuailed not. And they myght haue remedied it, yf they wolde haue ſuffred the emperoure to rule ouer them.<note place="margin">The empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure Titu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Veſpaſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> And al preuailed nothinge. They were deſtroyed, for they had diſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed gods worde. Euen ſo ſhall it happen vnto oure papiſtes alſo. It is propheſied vnto them by Dani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>el in the ſeuenth and eyght chapter, it is prophecied vnto them by Sacharia, in the eleuenth chapter, it prophecieth vnto them Iohn in his reuelacions, it prophecieth vnto them Chriſt him ſelfe. Mat xxiiii it is prophecied vnto them by Paule .ii. Teſſalo .ii. alſo .i. Timo. iiii. It is prophecied vnto them by Peter .ii. Pe. ii. It preuaileth not. There prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto them their owne byſhops, abbots, monkes and nonnes, it preuaileth not, it is prophecied vnto them by the aſtronomers, it is prophecied vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9430:32"/>
by the commun rumour with certaine prouerbes, it is prophetied vnto them by viſions and ſignes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> element, but all preuayleth not. They heare it and ſee it in acte, it preuaileth not. They myght tourne it, if they wolde not be aboue gods worde and mens conſciences. But woulde ſuffer god and his worde, to rule ouer them, and all mens conſciences, but all preuayleth nothinge. Therefore muſt they alſo be deſtroyed, there is no remedy, that muſte they ſee. Therefore let no good chriſtian frette hym ſelfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them. But rather ſuffer and take pacience and pray vnto God, that it will pleaſe hym to reuenge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhed bloude of his ſaintes, and ſhortly to delyuer vs of theſe cruell tirantes. Thereby ſhall a man get more vppon them, then by ſworde and harnyſſhe. God knoweth well a Titus, that ſhal deſtroye theſe Iewes alſo. Amen.</p>
               <p>Thus endeth the beginning and ending of all poperye or popyſſhe kyngdome, taken out of olde prophecies, more then thre houndreth yeres paſt to the amendemente of thys preſent worlde. ſet forth out of hye Almayne into englyſhe by Gwalter Lynne.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:9430:33"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Printed at London in Aldergate ſtrete, by Iohn Herforde, at the coſtes and charges of Gwalter Lynne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuiligio ad imprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9430:33"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
